<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[theBeginning.life]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Beginning of Jesus Christ's Good News]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life/</link><image><url>https://thebeginning.life//logos/logo-48.png</url><title>theBeginning.life</title><link>https://thebeginning.life/</link></image><generator>GatsbyJS Advanced Starter</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 05:22:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://thebeginning.life//rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[Copyright © 2020. All rights reserved.]]></copyright><item><title><![CDATA[Principles of translation]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">Because this is the beginning</span>
The purpose in preparing this translation is to faithfully update the American Standard Version of Mark into contemporary spoken American…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//principles-of-translation</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//principles-of-translation</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Because this is the beginning&lt;/span&gt;
The purpose in preparing this translation is to faithfully update the American Standard Version of Mark into contemporary spoken American English as used by those who don’t already know anything of the Bible, have no theology background, and are generally unfamiliar with church culture.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not have a technical background in Bible translation and are still interested, read on.  I will do my best to remain understandable for you too but some of the following will necessarily use scholarly language in order to communicate as clearly as possible with scholars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;More technically…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Beginning of Life&lt;/em&gt; is an updated translation of the book of Mark.  It is a direct derivative work of the &lt;em&gt;American Standard Version&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldenglish.bible&quot;&gt;World English Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (WEB) translations of the Bible.  The WEB is itself a partial update of the American Standard Version translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Overall principles of translation&lt;/span&gt;
In preparing this translation, I have drawn on the underlying Greek and/or Hebrew, the rest of the Bible, other modern English translations of the Bible, and scholarly input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The translation is heavily biased toward formal equivalance in vocabulary, resorting to dynamic equivalence when necessary.  When dynamic equivalence is used to translate a technical term, the formal equivalent and/or traditional translation is preserved as a side note next to the text.  I have used this and other typographical conventions to help with readability while maintaining accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formally-equivalent word orderings are preferred but this is heavily in tension with this work’s readability goals.  I have included detailed explanations about various ways I resolve this tension below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Typographical conventions&lt;/span&gt;
Here is an exhaustive list of these conventions: [^{-} These owe a great debt to the work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://edwardtufte.github.io/tufte-css/&quot;&gt;Edward Tufte&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is some text&lt;label for=&quot;md-this-is-a-study-note&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-this-is-a-study-note&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is a study note with context helpful for understanding the text.&lt;/span&gt; that might benefit from additional context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;A theme from this thing.&lt;/span&gt;Describes what happens in the text immediately following.  Typeset as a header (in a lighter typeface than the text).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Translation note.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Traditional, alternative, or more literal ways to translate a word or phrase. (Avoids textual criticism because of the audience.)  Used especially when the translation resorts to dynamic equivalence in order to keep itself honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Verse 1, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cross reference,&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Jhn.1.1-14&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jhn 1:1-14&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; hyperlinked to the NLT translation on &lt;em&gt;bible.com&lt;/em&gt;.  Used to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link to Old Testament passages when they are quoted or alluded to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link to other Bible passages that further explain what Mark is saying and/or offer context regarding the current topic in the text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Typographical challenges&lt;/span&gt;
The underlying text is maintained in plain text files using an extended Markdown-derived markup language.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently the only drawback of this format is that it offers no way to properly typeset poetry, render “acolon” and “bcolon” lines, etc.  These are currently typeset as a blockquote using line breaks to separate poetry sections from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Principles of English style&lt;/span&gt;
This work seeks to render Mark’s gospel in modern spoken English in a colloquial and yet reverent style.  Here are some examples of what this means to this author:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shorter sentences, fragments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s okay to start a sentence with a connector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And contractions are okay too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently targeting a 9th or 10th grade (US) reading level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Word ordering and formal vs. dynamic equivalence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At best, Greek word ordering is bad English style to native English speakers and is confusing to understand at worst. This reworking should respect principles of excellent English style while retaining the academic rigor present in the original ASV text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result should be immediately understandable by unchurched or lightly-churched individuals without eliminating challenges faced by all faithful interpreters of the Bible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offensive or confusing things Jesus said and did are retained and not explained. Metaphors that Jesus or Mark used are retained because these add depth and dimension to their context that otherwise would be lost.  Also, many symbols and metaphors appear in a remarkably consistent way throughout the Bible so this author believes that retaining the symbols and metaphors is important to developing a cohesive understanding of the entire Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Detailed notes on formal versus dynamic equivalence&lt;/span&gt;
The ASV is a formal equivalence translation. Retain this rigor in the update within the structure of what would be considered excellent (if colloquial, spoken) English style. On the other hand, all translation work necessarily has an element of interpretation–particularly when a word in the source language does not have a direct equivalent in the target language. In these situations, switch to dynamic equivalence while remaining as close to formal equivalence as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These goals can be in tension with each other. The following principles guide how I have resolved these tensions. I’ve included specific examples where needed to clearly explain a thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retain Mark’s “overuse” of the word “immediately”. It is this author’s belief that Mark is intentionally using repetition to make a point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a global mechanical search-and-replace update works, use it to retain continuity with the underlying Greek when possible. For example: &lt;em&gt;Behold&lt;/em&gt; → &lt;em&gt;Look!&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;wilderness&lt;/em&gt; → &lt;em&gt;desert&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;multitude&lt;/em&gt; → &lt;em&gt;large crowd; great multitude → very large crowd.&lt;/em&gt;, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When appropriate, change to active voice. For example, in 1:26: “The unclean spirit convulsed the man, shrieked loudly, and came out of him.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simplify wording of lists to modern spoken English standards. 1:26 above is an example of this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A single thought gets a single sentence. Closely-related thoughts or those utilizing parallelism get a single sentence with semicolons separating each thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break up excessively long sentances.  But be careful to retain relative emphasis among thoughts present in the original.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used sparingly, sometimes sentance fragments can be effective as long as they don’t change the relative emphasis between the idea in the fragment and the run-on sentance being broken up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many times the English is confusing because Mark used pronouns excessively or the referent of an expression is unclear without carefully studying the grammar of the context. While this may be the way Mark wrote, this is not considered high-quality spoken or written English. Resolve pronouns and other referents to their antecedents when doing this yields a clearer and equally-accurate reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use parentheses and hyphens (as appropriate) when a thought is interrupted by another one. Prefer using punctuation over rearranging word order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rearrange word order only judiciously and being careful to preserve the emphases each individual idea in a sentence receives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a direct or indirect object is separated from its referent, rearrange the word order to bring them together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, 2:14: As he passed by the tax office, he saw Levi the son of Alphaeus working there. Here the ASV (and the Greek) separates “passed by” from its indirect object “the tax office” with an interjection about Jesus meeting Levi there. Putting the IO next to its verb makes the sentence immediately more comprehensible to a modern reader and also clarifies the fact that Levi was a tax collector.  This also clarifies the following story beginning in verse 18, without adding or removing from what was said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t translate symbols or metaphors. The Bible expects a lot of its reader and that’s ok.  See above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a thing would be obvious to one of Mark’s original readers but not to a modern reader, clarify it using rewording, a parenthetical comment, hyphens, etc.  Add a sidenote to preserve accountability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Translate technical theological terms whenever necessary for comprehension among today’s largely-unchurched youth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with the Greek literal translation.  Sometimes this directly offers an excellent substitute.  For example in 1:4, &lt;em&gt;baptize&lt;/em&gt; → &lt;em&gt;ceremonially immerse [in water]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the immediate context.  For example, Mark uses the word &lt;em&gt;baptize&lt;/em&gt; in two ways: the ceremonial way described above and also when &lt;em&gt;preaching baptism [of repentance for the forgiveness of sins]&lt;/em&gt;.  This latter case can borrow from the context immediately preceeding combined with appropriate translation sidenotes: &lt;em&gt;need to immerse their affections[^ *a baptism&lt;/em&gt;] in God’s straight paths instead of their own&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;of repentance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.*  See below for more examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the weight of Scripture.  Sometimes another scripture provides an excellent explanation or definition.  Continuing in verse 4, “a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness &lt;em&gt;of sins.”&lt;/em&gt;  Here “sins” is used in general sense, so we need a concise, faithful expression describing “sin” in the general sense.  Here we can still let Scripture interpret Scripture by rendering this as “forgiven for &lt;em&gt;preferring selfish pleasure (and the hurt that this causes) instead”&lt;/em&gt; along with a cross-reference to &lt;em&gt;James 4:1-3&lt;/em&gt; from where this idea was directly lifted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;More discussion about translating technical theological terms&lt;/span&gt;
Repent / repentance: These words aren’t used at all in modern spoken English and especially not among our unchurched youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin: In colloquial English, this word simply means “a bad thing” or “a bad person”. But in common use today when the word is used at all it is frequently used in an ironic or sarcastic way. The effect is to change “sin” from an undesirable to a desirable thing—and sometimes even makes fun of the whole concept of sin to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theologically this is beyond inaccurate. Further, we would rarely-to-never refer to someone as a “sinner” in spoken English in the Bible sense of the word outside a church (or even inside most churches). As a result, this author believes the word “sin” has completely lost its meaning in spoken English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other concerns happen because different parts of languages change differently over time so some English words’ meaning may still be largely faithful but need elaboration or careful adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some of these cases I have felt it more appropriate to include the theological term used in the text, but with a (usually parenthetical) elaboration or explanation in the context.  &lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes I’ve used a sidenote to clarify the original authorial intent when retaining a traditional rendering.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other cases, I have found that an English word that is closely related to or derived from the original word that hasn’t yet lost its Bible meaning and connotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, our culture’s understanding of &lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt; is more-or-less accurate–but only if one disregards that atheists and many scientists believe that faith is fundamentally an irrational or unscientific thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, I believe that perhaps the word &lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt; itself may not be wise to use in a modern English translation.  However, in common use words derived from &lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt; remain &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; to the Bible meaning, and in many cases we can &lt;em&gt;faithfully&lt;/em&gt; use those to substitute for and/or to clarify in situations where &lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt; is called for.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why is this project important?]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">Post-Christian America</span>
My experience speaking with others of my generation (commonly known as generation X) about the Bible and about Christianity has been that, most…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//why-is-this-project-important</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//why-is-this-project-important</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Post-Christian America&lt;/span&gt;
My experience speaking with others of my generation (commonly known as generation X) about the Bible and about Christianity has been that, most people are aware of the Bible meanings of theological words and ideas as presented in modern translations.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, people in my generation generally know what a Christian means when s/he uses words like “sin”, “repent”, “righteous”, “Satan”, “evil spirit, unclean spirit, demon”, etc.  And many in my generation have a cultural understanding of the Good News–at least enough to be innoculated to it and have their preconceived reasons for rejecting it.  That is the bad news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the good news for my generation is that many who are hungry to know the God of the Bible already have the required background to understand the Bible using many of the excellent modern translations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand (in my own experience) many from the younger generation that is coming of age right now have none of this background understanding of theological terms needed to become a disciple of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is both an opportunity and a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The hunger&lt;/span&gt;
In my experience, I have never met a group of people more hungry to know about God generally and the God of the Bible specifically than this younger generation.  I regularly experience members of this generation immediately ask me to teach them how to know God as soon as they learn that I am a Christian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The challenge&lt;/span&gt;
Unfortunately, my experience has also been that when they try to read modern Bible translations these same people quickly bog down in technical theological terms like those listed above and lose interest.  Forcing technical theological terms on new disciples of Jesus right at the beginning of their walk in my own experience has proven profoundly counter-productive to the Church’s mission to make disciples of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The opportunity&lt;/span&gt;
Mark’s stated objective at the start of his book is to present “the &lt;em&gt;beginning&lt;/em&gt; of the Good News of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.”  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I believe that if we take Mark’s word as gospel (inspired by the Holy Spirit) this offers a simple, straightforward, and direct way to become a true disciple of Jesus Christ as well as to make disciples of Jesus Christ as he commanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Romans Road,&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;four spiritual laws,&lt;/em&gt; along with programs like &lt;em&gt;Evangelism Explosion&lt;/em&gt; and others have borne fruit.  Many have found their way to becoming a disciple of Jesus through these synopses of the Good News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I believe that starting with Mark (because he alone claims to start at the beginning) and studying sequentially and &lt;em&gt;inductively&lt;/em&gt; offers a more direct road into Jesus the Truth, Christ the Door, Jesus the Way, and Jesus the Life.  This approach depends simply on obtaining a faithful translation of Mark that itself translates these theological and/or cultural terms into understandable colloquial spoken English that any random native English speaker would readily comprehend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been able to find others with this vision, so I am beginning this work myself, in the open, hoping that others with skillsets complimenting my own offer their own expertise.  And hoping that in the end this work becomes an effort representative of the Body of Christ herself and her mission to effectively make disciples of Jesus before the last day comes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;My own skillset&lt;/span&gt;
I became a disciple of Jesus Christ as a middle-schooler and have been a passionate student of the Bible since.  While I have experienced seasons during which my strength or my total commitment to Jesus has faltered, I have never let go of my fundamental profound desire to be a disciple of Jesus and a student of the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a Hebrew or Greek scholar but my wife is a Biblical Hebrew scholar and I’m not afraid of Greek interlinears and/or Hebrew/Greek lexicons.  These are a regular part of my personal study of the Scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding Bible translation, I served a summer internship with Wycliffe Bible Translators as a high school student, grew up in the same church as Ken Taylor who originally updated the ASV–the result being published as The Living Bible paraphrase.  I am a friendly acquaintance of Mark Taylor (Ken’s son), and am familiar with many of the theological and political considerations surrounding a “layperson” updating an existing translation and having it remain properly a trustworthy translation instead of a “mere paraphrase.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main personal weakness is that I have very little background in textual criticism, and while I understand some fundamental principles such as “the ‘harder reading’ more likely being original” I cannot hope to evaluate alternate renderings myself the way a scholar with this training could.  To remediate this deficiency, I am relying on scholarly textual notes in the NET Bible 2.0, other study Bibles, and other readily-available scholarly resources.  And if any of these suggest an alternate rendering to be more accurate than the traditional ASV translation, I’ll cite my source(s)–probably in a footnote but this is undecided as this concern has yet to present itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, if a scholar with experience in Bible translation and (particularly with) expertise in textual criticism wishes to help address any possible weaknesses I bring in this area, I would be delighted to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Jesus's arrival]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">The beginning of the Good News of Jesus</span>
Here is not a baby in a manger.  Here is not a child who wise kings searched for with gifts.  Instead, Mark is laser-focused on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Introducing his reader to Jesus.</li>
<li>Explaining Jesus’s purpose for coming.</li>
<li>Inviting his reader to make a conscious choice based on this information.</li>…</ul>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//jesuss-arrival</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//jesuss-arrival</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The beginning of the Good News of Jesus&lt;/span&gt;
Here is not a baby in a manger.  Here is not a child who wise kings searched for with gifts.  Instead, Mark is laser-focused on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing his reader to Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explaining Jesus’s purpose for coming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inviting his reader to make a conscious choice based on this information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How?   Here is a summary of the choices Mark invites his reader to make:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To admit that our life’s paths haven’t always been straight.  Sometimes they have been crooked.  The first thing, then, is to straighten our paths as much as we know how to do.  Apologize to anyone we have wronged and do whatever is needed to make it right.  Apologize–most of all–to God whose loving principles we have disregarded, preferring selfish pleasure instead. &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-1#1&quot;&gt;Mrk 1:1&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a name=&quot;mkxr&quot; href=&quot;/mark-1#6&quot;&gt;Mrk 1:6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To recognize Jesus as the Ruler–and invite him to be our own ruler too. &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-1#3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 1:3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To know Jesus as King–and to pledge our allegiance to him. &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-1#15&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 1:15&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/span&gt;
These are difficult things to ask anyone to consider.  The rest of Mark’s book offers the information we need to decide how we will respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you read, I encourage you to expectantly trust that God will help you to understand and will help you know how to respond.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">Jesus receives a man who spares no cost to come…</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>A number of days later Jesus returned to Capernaum and the news quickly spread that he was at home.</p>
<p><small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>Immediately a…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-2</guid><category><![CDATA[heal]]></category><category><![CDATA[tradition]]></category><category><![CDATA[in-n-out]]></category><category><![CDATA[hunger]]></category><category><![CDATA[word-picture]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus receives a man who spares no cost to come…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A number of days later Jesus returned to Capernaum and the news quickly spread that he was at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately a crowd gathered and soon there was no more room, not even around the door.  And Jesus spoke the word to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Four people came, carrying a paralyzed man to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they couldn’t get close to Jesus because of the crowd, they broke and removed the roof above Jesus! Then (with the roof removed), they lowered the mat where the paralyzed man was lying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus, recognizing their expectant trust that he could and would help,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Heb.11.NLT&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heb 11&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; said to the paralyzed man, “Son, your selfish tendencies and choices&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are forgiven.”&lt;label for=&quot;md-jesus-healed-many&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-jesus-healed-many&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Jesus healed many people previously.  This is the first time he forgave too.  How was this man different from the others?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But inflexible religious tradition is offended&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But some of the religious experts who were scribes were sitting there reasoning silently in their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Why does this man defame and insult God like that?  It’s blasphemy!  Who can forgive all of another person’s selfish tendencies and choices&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; except for God–and only him?” they thought to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately Jesus perceived in his spirit that they reasoned silently this way so he asked them, “Why do you question and criticize?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Which is easier to tell a paralyzed person:  ‘Your sins are forgiven’ or, ‘Get up, pick up your bed, and walk?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But to prove that the &lt;em&gt;Son of Man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-this-new-title-less&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-this-new-title-less&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This new title, &lt;em&gt;Son of Man,&lt;/em&gt; is a reference to Daniel’s prophesy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Dan.7.13-15&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan 7:13-15&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Dan.7.9-28&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan 7:9-28&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-this-is-the-first&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-this-is-the-first&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is the first time Jesus claimed to be God.&lt;/span&gt; has authority on earth to forgive sins” (Jesus then addressed the paralyzed man) &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Get up, pick up your mat, and return home.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The man got up, immediately picked up his mat, and went out in front of them all! Everyone was amazed; they spoke with soaring words about God!&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;or: glorified God&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; “We have never seen anything like this!” they said.&lt;label for=&quot;md-religious-tradition&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-religious-tradition&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Religious Tradition now has a choice: will they accept Jesus’s kingly authority as superior to their current religious understanding or will they oppose him?  Those of us with religious traditions have the same choice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus is close to people who recognize their own need…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus returned to the seashore; a very large crowd came together, and Jesus taught them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As he passed the tax office, he saw Levi the son of Alphaeus working there. “Follow me,” Jesus said. And Levi got up and followed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Later, Jesus was reclining at the meal table in Levi’s house, and many other tax collectors and socially unacceptable “sinners” sat down with Jesus and his students;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; there were many of these kinds of people, and they followed Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But Religious Tradition is offended by Jesus’s openness toward people who know their hearts are sick&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But the religious experts who were scribes and conservative teachers known as Pharisees questioned Jesus’s students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; when they saw him eating with the “sinners” and tax collectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why does Jesus eat and drink with tax collectors and ‘sinners’?” these respected religious teachers asked Jesus’s students.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Overhearing this, Jesus replied, “Those who are healthy don’t need a doctor, but sick people do. I didn’t come to call people who think they are right in God’s sight,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the ‘righteous’, but Jesus is being sarcastic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; but people who ultimately prefer pursuing selfish pleasure&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sinners&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to recognize the hurt that this choice causes and to have a deep, profound change of heart.”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;to repentance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Religious tradition is blind to who Jesus is…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;John’s students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and some Pharisees–religious Conservatives–were fasting by temporarily going without something to instead focus more clearly on God. They came to Jesus and questioned, “Why do John’s students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and the Pharisees’ students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; fast, but your students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; don’t fast?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered, “Can the honored groomsmen at a wedding deprive themselves while the bridegroom is with them?  As long as they have the bridegroom with them, they can’t fast.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But the days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and beginning that day they will fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-to-escape-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-to-escape-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 To escape religious tradition, a person needs a new covering for one’s naked shame and flexibility to receive the new wine.  The new clothes and the flexibility to receive the new wine are obtained by choosing the Ruler’s roads over our own selfish cultural preferences and accepting God’s forgiveness with expectant trust.  The new wine itself (that causes us to grow) is obtained by hearing and applying Jesus’s teaching.&lt;/span&gt;“Nobody patches an old shrunken piece of clothes using new fabric that hasn’t shrunk yet. Otherwise when the new patch shrinks, it will tear away from the old cloth; it will make a worse hole than before.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;No one puts new wine into old (brittle) wine-skins; otherwise when the new wine ferments it will expand, cause the old skins to burst, the wine to pour out, and the wine-skins to be destroyed. Instead, they put new wine into fresh wine-skins.”&lt;label for=&quot;md-jesus-reaches-out-to&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-jesus-reaches-out-to&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Jesus reaches out to all those whose religious traditions get in the way of God’s Kingdom in their lives–and explains how to escape.  The sheer number of stories Mark tells about this topic indicates how difficult this can be.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But those who recognize their hunger are filled&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;On the Sabbath day Jesus and his students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; were going through some grain fields and his students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; began to pick ears of grain to eat.&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Lev.19.9-10&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lev 19:9-10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Law of Moses explicitly permitted poor people to eat grain from the corners of others’ fields.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Look! why do they do what is against (traditional religious) law on the sacred Sabbath day?” these religious Conservatives&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pharasees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; objected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “Didn’t you ever read what David did when he was needy, when he was hungry?&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/1Sa.20.NLT&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1Sa 20&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  He, along with those who were with him?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Do you remember how David entered God’s house when Abiathar was high priest and ate the ceremonial show bread? And do you remember how it is against the Law of Moses for anyone to eat the temple bread except for the priests–but David ate it and gave some to those who were with him too?” &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/1Sa.21.1-6&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1Sa 21:1-6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to them,&lt;label for=&quot;md-these-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-these-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 These religious conservatives were unwilling to be flexible about their traditional laws, much less learn how to apply the Law of Moses correctly from Jesus.  Ultimately, their allegiance was to their own Religious “Kingdom” and its earthly political power instead of to God’s kingdom.&lt;/span&gt; “The special Sabbath day was made to meet people’s needs, not men and women for the Sabbath.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Therefore the &lt;em&gt;Son of Man&lt;/em&gt; is The Ruler, even over the Sabbath!”&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">Jesus heals a man’s deformed hand on the sacred Sabbath day…</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>Jesus entered the synagogue again, and a man was there whose hand was deformed.</p>
<p><small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>Jesus’s religious enemies…<label for="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote"><em>e.g.: accuse him of working on the sacred Sabbath day of rest</em></span></p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-3</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-3</guid><category><![CDATA[in-n-out]]></category><category><![CDATA[choose]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus heals a man’s deformed hand on the sacred Sabbath day…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus entered the synagogue again, and a man was there whose hand was deformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus’s religious enemies watched to see if he would heal the man on the Sabbath day so they could accuse him.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g.: accuse him of working on the sacred Sabbath day of rest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to the man whose hand was deformed, “Stand up.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then Jesus addressed his enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Does the Law&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g.: the Law of Moses found in the books of Exodus through Deuteronomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; intend for a person to do good to others or to harm others on the Sabbath day? To save a life or to kill?” Jesus asked.&lt;label for=&quot;md-jesus-offers-his&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-jesus-offers-his&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Jesus offers his enemies another opportunity to change–to accept the good news of his kingdom with expectant trust.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His enemies were silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus looked around at them with anger (out of grief because his enemies’ hearts were becoming harder and harder), then said to the man, “Stretch out your hand.” The man stretched it out and his hand was restored as healthy as the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But the religious Conservatives preferred the man stay disabled&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The religious Conservatives&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pharasees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; left and immediately conspired against Jesus with the “Pro King Herod” political party;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herodians&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; together they began planning to kill him.&lt;label for=&quot;md-herod-was-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-herod-was-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Herod was the corrupt puppet king installed by Rome to rule over Israel.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Religious preferences can be a form of selfish comfort–a comfort that we are “right” and others are “wrong.”  If allowed to be more important than Jesus himself, these preferences and convictions will ultimately kill God’s kingdom in our lives.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The followers: people who liked Jesus&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus went back to the sea with his students;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; a huge crowd followed him from Galilee, from Judea, &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;from Jerusalem, from Idumaea, from beyond the Jordan, and from the area around Tyre and Sidon.  When Jesus arrived, an enormous crowd gathered made up of people who had heard about the amazing things Jesus was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The students: people who joined Jesus, who learned, and who helped&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus asked his students&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;apprentices or disciples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to keep a little boat nearby because of the crowd pressing toward him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus had healed many and those who had diseases pressed toward him; they were trying to touch him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The evil spirits (whenever they saw Jesus) fell down before him shouting, “You are the Son of God!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus sternly warned them not to tell people who he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The twelve: people who spoke for Jesus with his authority&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus climbed a mountain and called to those he wanted.  And they came.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He appointed twelve:&lt;label for=&quot;md-everyone-jesus-calls&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-everyone-jesus-calls&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Everyone Jesus calls close to himself is important, and he knows them by name.&lt;/span&gt; to be close to him, to send out and speak God’s word, &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and to have authority to heal sicknesses and cast out demons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Simon, to whom he gave the name Peter;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;James the son of Zebedee; and John, the brother of James, (whom he called Boanerges, which means, Sons of Thunder);  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Andrew; Philip; Bartholomew; Matthew; Thomas; James, the son of Alphaeus; Thaddaeus; Simon the Zealot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Those outside and those inside&lt;/span&gt;
Then Jesus came to his home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The large crowd gathered together again, so that those inside could not eat bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus’s friends heard the news they came to take custody of him; they said, “He is insane!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The religious leaders who were scribes from Jerusalem said, “He has Beelzebul&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beelzebul was the name gentile nations used for Satan, the chief demon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; inside him!” and, “He casts out demons using power the ruler of the demons gave him!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; Jesus called for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using illustrations&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;parables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to make his point Jesus asked, “How can Satan&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: accuser or plaintiff; the chief demon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; cast out Satan?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom can’t stand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If a family&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;house&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; fights against itself, that family will break apart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If Satan&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;see note on verse 23&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; rebels against himself and is divided he can’t stand. He is finished!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Nobody can enter the Strong Man’s house and ransack it unless he first ties up the Strong Man; then he can ransack his house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“I say with certainty: all of peoples’ selfish intentions and actions will be forgiven, including flagrant disrespect&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;blasphemy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; with which they may defame&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;blaspheme&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“But whoever deliberately defames and slanders&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;blasphemes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (actions performed by) the Holy Spirit never has forgiveness;&lt;label for=&quot;md-inflexible-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-inflexible-religious&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Inflexible Religious Tradition is an enemy of God’s Kingdom.  If allowed to live in one’s heart it ultimately kills.&lt;/span&gt; their guilt never ends.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;—because the religious leaders said, “A demon owns him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The mother and brothers of Jesus came.  Standing outside, they sent for Jesus and called to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A large crowd was sitting around Jesus, and they told him, “Look! your mother, your brothers, and your sisters are outside looking for you.”&lt;label for=&quot;md-mark-has-described&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-mark-has-described&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Mark has described the inflexibly religious, the casual followers, the students, and the twelve.  Which kind of person are you most like right now?  If you want to join Jesus, all he requires is that you set your affections on the things God wants and that you do these things as best as you know how right now.  He will take care of the rest.  Can you do that much?  Ask Jesus and he will help.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; Jesus answered them, “Who are my mother and my brothers?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Looking around at those who sat around him, he said, “Look! my mother and my brothers!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Whoever does the things God asks him or her to do is my brother, my sister, and mother.”&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 4]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">The teaching to understand all the other teachings</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>Jesus returned to the seaside to teach.  A huge crowd gathered, so Jesus got into a boat in the water and sat down…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-4</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-4</guid><category><![CDATA[hear]]></category><category><![CDATA[choose]]></category><category><![CDATA[word-picture]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The teaching to understand all the other teachings&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus returned to the seaside to teach.  A huge crowd gathered, so Jesus got into a boat in the water and sat down; the crowd listened from the land nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus taught the crowd many things using word-pictures as illustrations.  Speaking urgently, Jesus began to teach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Carefully listen and see:”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: spoke saying ‘Listen!  Look! …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of the seed and the soil&lt;/span&gt;
“A farmer went out to plant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“As he spread his seeds some fell next to the road; the birds came and ate them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Other seeds fell on rocky ground where there was little soil.  Immediately plants sprang up (because the soil wasn’t deep) but &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;when the sun rose it scorched the seed.  Because the seed’s roots had no depth the plants withered away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Other seeds fell among thorns and the thorns grew up and choked them; they didn’t yield any fruit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Other seeds fell into good soil, grew to maturity, and yielded fruit.  Some produced thirty times, some sixty times, and some one hundred times as much as was originally planted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“If anyone’s heart is open to hear, that person must carefully listen!”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;If anyone has ‘ears to hear’ let him hear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus explains his illustrations to those who stay with him&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Later–after the crowds left Jesus alone–those who lingered with him,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;those around him&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; along with the twelve, asked him to explain this illustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “God has given you the mysteries of his Kingdom;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;To you has been given the mysteries of God’s kingdom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; I only offer illustrations to those who are outside it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;This is so that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While seeing they may “see” but not perceive,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Jer.5.21-29&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jer 5:21-29&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Ezk.12.2-3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ezk 12:2-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And while hearing they may “hear” and not understand;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Otherwise they might turn around,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And their selfish preferences and choices be forgiven.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus continued, “Don’t you understand this illustration?&lt;label for=&quot;md-e-g-this&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-e-g-this&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 e.g.: This illustration is the key to understanding the rest of Jesus’s teachings.&lt;/span&gt; If not, how will you understand all the other ones?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The Word is beyond value and everything that detracts from it is destructive&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“The farmer spreads the Word.”&lt;label for=&quot;md-in-jesus-s-day&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-in-jesus-s-day&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;In Jesus’s day farmers scattered seeds across the ground; it would be normal for seed to land elsewhere than in the field.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The first are people&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;These are beside the road where the Word is spread; when they hear…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; who are beside the road where the word is spread!&lt;label for=&quot;md-the-farmer-s-plow&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-the-farmer-s-plow&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 The farmer’s plow can break the most hardened dirt road so it can receive the seed.&lt;/span&gt;  When they hear the Word, immediately Satan comes and takes&lt;label for=&quot;md-1-to-steal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-1-to-steal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;1) to steal&lt;/span&gt; the Word that the farmer planted in them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The next seeds landed on shallow rocky soil.&lt;label for=&quot;md-the-farmer-can-dig&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-the-farmer-can-dig&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 The farmer can dig out the rocks that prevent roots from going deep.&lt;/span&gt;  When people are shallow rocky soil and hear the Word they immediately receive it with delight!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But the Word’s roots cannot grow deep in their hearts and they only live a short time.  When they begin to experience trouble or hostility because they received the Word, immediately they are bitterly offended and leave.&lt;label for=&quot;md-2-to-kill&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-2-to-kill&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;2) to kill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Other seeds land among thorns.&lt;label for=&quot;md-the-farmer-can-dig&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-the-farmer-can-dig&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 The farmer can dig out the thorny distractions that ultimately scratch us, entangle us, and destroy the Word.&lt;/span&gt;  When people are thorny soil, they hear the Word–but other things in their lives present themselves as alternatives to the Word.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The world’s distractions are one alternative.  The mirage of being satisfied by material things,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;deceitfulness of wealth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is another.  Being preoccupied with other things is another alternative to the Word.  These things all crowd out the Word and cause it to be unfruitful!&lt;label for=&quot;md-3-to-destroy-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-3-to-destroy-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;3) to destroy the Word’s fruitfulness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But there is seed that lands on good ground.&lt;label for=&quot;md-we-all-begin-as&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-we-all-begin-as&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 We all begin as unfruitful soil.  But the farmer is capable of making each kind of unfruitful soil healthy.  When we are made healthy in these ways, the natural result is expectant trust that the seed will grow, mature, and bear fruit–so we welcome it gladly into our hearts.&lt;/span&gt;  These people hear the Word, accept it, and are fertile soil bearing fruit.  Some of these people multiply the Word thirty times, some sixty times, and some one hundred times beyond what they received!”&lt;label for=&quot;md-4-life-rich-and&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-4-life-rich-and&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;4) life, rich and satisfying&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Jhn.10.10&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jhn 10:10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;It’s God’s privilege to conceal things and the king’s privilege to discover them&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus continued, “Is an oil lamp brought to a place&lt;label for=&quot;md-a-basket-s-purpose&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-a-basket-s-purpose&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 A basket’s purpose is to help with human labor; a bed’s purpose is to aid our rest.  The light doesn’t belong under either one, but in its own rightful place.&lt;/span&gt; in order to be put under a basket or under a bed? Isn’t it put on a stand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Nothing is hidden except for it to be discovered, and every secret is intended to be illuminated.&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Pro.25.2&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro 25:2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“If anyone’s heart is open to hear, that person should carefully listen!”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;If anyone has ‘ears to hear’…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Value it, use it, and be generously given more–otherwise lose it&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said, “Pay careful attention to what you hear!  The metric you use to measure what you apply to your life will also be used to measure more back to you–along with a gracious bonus.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;and extra to you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Whoever makes what they hear part of themselves will be given more.  But the person who ignores what they hear,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g.: so it’s as if they don’t know it at all&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; even what that person genuinely has will be taken away.”&lt;label for=&quot;md-how-do-we-make-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-how-do-we-make-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 How do we make the teachings Jesus has offered so far part of ourselves?  Start with the three kinds of unfruitful soil above and apply each lesson to the degree you know how right now.  Here are some thoughts to get you started:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-1-what-habits-or&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-1-what-habits-or&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;1) What habits or well-worn paths keep you from hearing Jesus’s Word to begin with?  What attitudes keep you doing or thinking things you know are harmful?  List these and pray, asking God to help you change.  Then make a plan and begin changing.  Find someone else who can support you and keep you accountable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-2-are-you-aware-of&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-2-are-you-aware-of&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;2) Are you aware of any things you do that are unhealthy or harmful toward yourself or others?  If you are unwilling to change these things, they become like the stones that keep Jesus’s Word from taking root in your heart.  List these.  Leave no stone unturned.  Ask God for forgiveness.  If you have harmed somebody else, do whatever you are able to do to make it right and ask for their forgiveness too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-3-lastly-what-things&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-3-lastly-what-things&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;3) Lastly, what things are you passionate about?  Being passionate toward something isn’t bad by itself.  But it’s bad if you begin to love it more than you love Jesus so that you stop paying attention to Jesus and his Word.  Ask God for help and begin placing healthy boundaries on these things.  Eliminate them if necessary.  Nothing is more valuable than God’s kingdom.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of the seed and the earth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said, “God’s Kingdom is like a farmer spreading seed on the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“The man sleeps and wakes night and day and the seed germinates and grows–even though the man doesn’t fully understand how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“The earth produces fruit by itself: first the blade, then the ear, then the mature grain in the ear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“But when the fruit is ripe, immediately the farmer cuts the stalks down using his sickle–because the harvest has arrived.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of the mustard seed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus continued, “What is God’s Kingdom like?  What word-picture illustrates it well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“God’s Kingdom is like a single mustard seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even though it’s the smallest seed &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;at planting time, it grows and matures into a larger plant than the other garden plants.  It grows large branches and birds from high places&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;of the heavens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; nest in its shade.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus used many similar illustrations to explain the Word, up to the amount they could hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;It’s God’s privilege to conceal things and the king’s privilege to discover them (reprise)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus no longer spoke to the crowd except through illustrations!&lt;label for=&quot;md-when-jesus-no-longer&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-when-jesus-no-longer&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 When Jesus no longer speaks in a way we can understand, something is very wrong.  But Mark tells us the way back: a) to spend private time with Jesus; b) to stay persistently where he is.&lt;/span&gt;  But he explained everything privately to his students who stayed with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of the boat and the storm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;That evening Jesus said, “Let’s go to the other side of the sea.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Leaving the huge crowd, the students took Jesus with them and got into the boat; other small boats joined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A large wind-storm rose and the waves broke into the boat–so badly that the boat was nearly swamped!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus was in the back of the boat, asleep on a cushion!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His students woke him up demanding, “Teacher!  Don’t you care that we are dying?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus woke up and corrected the wind!  He commanded the sea, “Silence!  Be still!”  The wind suddenly stopped and a great calm came over the sea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus asked the students, “Why are you so afraid?  Why don’t you have expectant trust&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; instead?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were deeply frightened and asked each other, “Who is this?  Even the wind and the sea obey him!”&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">An invitation; a new beginning</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>The beginning<label for="md-mark-s-book-is-the" class="margin-toggle ">&#8853;</label><input type="checkbox" id="md-mark-s-book-is-the" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="marginnote">🔑 Mark’s book is the only one in  that claims to start at the beginning./jesuss-arrival</span> of the Good News of Jesus: the one who God chose, the one with God’s approval, and the one with God’s own authority.<label for="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote"><em>Lit: Christ / Messiah / Anointed One</em></span>  The…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;An invitation; a new beginning&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The beginning&lt;label for=&quot;md-mark-s-book-is-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-mark-s-book-is-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Mark’s book is the only one in  that claims to start at the beginning./jesuss-arrival&lt;/span&gt; of the Good News of Jesus: the one who God chose, the one with God’s approval, and the one with God’s own authority.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: Christ / Messiah / Anointed One&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  The one who is the Son of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Prepare yourself–to be introduced to Jesus&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The prophets wrote–speaking for God himself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look! I am sending my messenger ahead of you;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;he will prepare your road ahead of time:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Mal.3.1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mal 3:1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;em&gt;the voice of one shouting in the desert,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Make The Ruler’s&lt;label for=&quot;md-who-is-the-ruler&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-who-is-the-ruler&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Who is the Ruler?  What is the nature of this Ruler’s authority?&lt;/span&gt; road ready!  Make his paths straight!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Isa.40.3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Isa 40:3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;John came, ceremonially immersing people (under water)&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;baptizing, which means “immersing”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in the desert and declaring peoples’ need to immerse their affections&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;a baptism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in God’s straight paths instead of their own.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;of repentance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  John said that when they fulfilled this condition they would be forgiven for preferring selfish pleasure&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Jas.4.1-3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jas 4:1-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (and the hurt that this causes) instead.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;for their sins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;All the country of Judea and all those of Jerusalem left their homes and towns to find John; he ceremonially immersed&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;baptized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; them in the Jordan river as they turned to God’s way.  They took responsibility for and began changing&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;repented&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the selfish paths they had chosen–paths that ultimately hurt themselves, God, and others as a consequence of their preference for selfish pleasure.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;of their sins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;John was clothed with camel’s hair, wore a leather belt around his waist, and ate locusts and wild honey for food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;John foretold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man will come after me who is more powerful than I am; out of deep respect it would not even be appropriate for me to stoop down and untie his sandal straps!”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am not worthy to stoop down and…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;I ceremonially immersed&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;baptized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; you in water, but he will immerse&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;baptize&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; you in the Holy Spirit–the One Spirit whose purpose&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;To be holy is to be uniquely set apart for a special purpose.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is to help you enter and follow God’s Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus chooses God’s road for his life&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In those days Jesus came from Nazareth (a town in Galilee) and John ceremonially immersed&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;baptized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; him in the Jordan river.&lt;label for=&quot;md-jesus-the-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-jesus-the-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Jesus (the ‘greater one’) was ceremonially immersed by John (the ‘lesser one’), indicating Jesus’s choice to follow God’s paths–no matter the personal cost.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Mrk.10.38-40&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 10:38-40&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately when Jesus broke the water’s surface, he saw the heavens splitting apart and the Holy Spirit descending on him in the form of a dove.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A voice came out of the sky, “You are my dearly-loved Son; I am delighted with you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately the Holy Spirit drove Jesus away from there into the desert.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He stayed in the desert forty days, tempted by Satan;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: Accuser or plaintiff; the chief evil spirit or demon (as opposed to the Holy Spirit, who is the Spirit of God.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; he was with the wild animals and the angels&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: God’s messengers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; were helping him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;There is a good kingdom and a perfect king&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now after John was arrested, Jesus entered Galilee declaring the Good News of God’s Kingdom. &lt;label for=&quot;md-jesus-is-the-kingly&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-jesus-is-the-kingly&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Jesus is the kingly Ruler who John and the prophets foretold.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“The time is fulfilled!  God’s Kingdom is here!” Jesus said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Change your citizenship from your own kingdom to God’s, surrender to his leadership, and align your own preferences to his values.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;repent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  And believe in the Good News!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;A king has authority over his followers’ lives&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Passing along the sea of Galilee, Jesus saw Simon and Andrew (Simon’s brother) casting a net into the sea; they worked as fishermen.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Follow me, and I will make you into fishers for men.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately they left their nets and followed him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Going on a little further from there, Jesus saw James, Zebedee’s son, and John his brother. (James and John were in their boat repairing their nets.)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately Jesus called to James and John and they left their father, Zebedee, in the boat with his hired helpers and followed Jesus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The king has authority to speak God’s word&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They entered Capernaum, and when the Sabbath day came Jesus immediately entered the synagogue and taught.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Everyone was amazed at his teaching because Jesus taught them like a person with authority, and not like the religious leaders who were scribes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The king has authority over demons&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately in their synagogue a man with a an evil spirit&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demons were also known as evil or unclean spirits; see also verse 32&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; shouted,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Ha! What do we have to do with you Jesus, you Nazarene? Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are: the Holy&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g.: Chosen; separated to a purpose of perfect good-will&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; One of God!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus strongly corrected the evil spirit!  “Be quiet! Come out of him!” Jesus commanded the spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The unclean spirit convulsed the man and shrieked loudly!  Then the evil spirit came out of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Everyone was amazed!  They all wondered about this!  They all discussed the news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What is this? A new teaching? Jesus even has authority to command the evil spirits!  And they obey him!” they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The news about Jesus immediately spread everywhere in the region known as “Galilee” and its surrounding area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The king has authority over sickness&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately, (when they had left the synagogue) they entered Simon and Andrew’s house with James and John.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now Simon’s wife’s mother lay sick with a fever and they told Jesus about her immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He came, took her by the hand, and raised her up. The fever immediately left her and she served them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In the evening after the sun had set people who knew about Jesus brought all who were sick and those who were possessed by demons to him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;All the city was gathered together at the door!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus healed many who were sick with various diseases and cast out many demons. He didn’t allow the demons to speak, because they knew him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus chooses God’s way over human expectations…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-mark-now-begins-a&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-mark-now-begins-a&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Mark now begins a series of stories that compare and contrast expectant trust in God with things that get in the way of expectant trust.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Early in the morning while it was still dark Jesus got up, went out, left Capernaum for a deserted place, and prayed there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Simon and those who were with him searched for Jesus. &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they found him they said, “Everyone is looking for you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “Let’s go somewhere else—into the next towns—so I can speak there too. This is why I came.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;So Jesus visited synagogues throughout the region of Galilee, speaking and casting out demons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But a sick man doesn’t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A man with the highly contagious, incurable, fatal skin disease known as&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;These characteristics of leprosy were common knowledge in Mark’s time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; leprosy found Jesus in order to beg.  Lowering himself to his knees in front of Jesus he said, “If you want to, you can make me clean!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;With deep compassion, Jesus stretched out his hand, touched the Leper&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lepers were a lower class in society, not just people with the disease known as leprosy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in reply and said, “I want to!  Be cleansed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus said this, immediately the leprosy left the man–he was made clean; he was completely healed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus strictly warned the man (immediately sending him on his way),  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Be careful that you don’t speak a word about this to anybody. Instead, go show yourself to the priest and offer the sacrifices Moses commanded for your cleansing. (This will be a witness to the priests.)”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;However, when the man left he told everybody and spread the news all over!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, Jesus couldn’t enter cities any more but instead stayed outside the cities in the desert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People still came to Jesus from all around.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 5]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">The illustration of two armies</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>They came to the other side of the sea, into the country of the Gadarenes.</p>
<p><small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>When Jesus left the boat, immediately a man with an evil spirit<label for="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote"><em>Lit: unclean spirit; also known as a demon</em></span>  ran from the tombs to meet him.  <small><sup class="verse" id="3">3 </sup></small>…<label for="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote"><em>or: the burial caves</em></span></p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-5</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-5</guid><category><![CDATA[heal]]></category><category><![CDATA[choose]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of two armies&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They came to the other side of the sea, into the country of the Gadarenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus left the boat, immediately a man with an evil spirit&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: unclean spirit; also known as a demon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  ran from the tombs to meet him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;This man lived in the tombs.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;or: the burial caves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody could tie or restrain him any more–not even using chains!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The people around frequently bound him using shackles and chains, but he tore the chains apart and broke the shackles in pieces. Nobody had the strength to subdue him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;All night, all day he wandered among the burial caves and the mountains; he was constantly shrieking and cutting himself with sharp stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When he saw Jesus from far away, he ran and bowed low to him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He roared, “What do I have to do with you–Jesus, you Son of the Most High God? I command you by God, don’t torture me!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;(Jesus had already said, “Come out of the man, you evil&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: unclean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; spirit!“)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus asked him, “What is your name?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said to Jesus, “My name is &lt;em&gt;Legion,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A legion was between 4000 and 6000 Roman soldiers.  The demons didn’t just emphasize that there were a lot of them, but used language indicating that they saw themselves as warriors prepared to fight for their kingdom and their king.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for we are many” &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and begged Jesus over and over not to send them away–out of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now a large herd of pigs was feeding there on the side of the hill.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And the demons begged Jesus, “Send us into the pigs!  Allow us to enter them!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus gave them permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the evil&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: unclean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; spirits came out of the man, entered the pigs, and the herd of about two thousand pigs rushed down the steep hillside into the sea where they drowned!&lt;label for=&quot;md-satan-is-a-liar-he&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-satan-is-a-liar-he&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Satan is a liar.  He promises pleasure but those who dedicate their lives to his cause ultimately find destruction.  Jesus is more powerful than Satan and his legions.  Renounce Satan’s kingdom, love of violence, and every form of occult practice, dedicate your life to God’s perfect kingdom, and expectantly trust Jesus.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Those who fed the pigs ran away in fear, spreading the news in the city and in the country!  And the people came to see what had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The crowd did not understand who Jesus is…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The people came to Jesus, saw the man who had been possessed by demons sitting, clothed, and in his right mind–yes even this man who had the legion of evil spirits–and they were afraid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The eyewitnesses explained to the crowd what happened to the man who had been demon-possessed and also to the pigs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then the crowd begged Jesus to leave their region!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…But the man who was delivered from the devils did&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As Jesus entered the boat to leave, the man who had been possessed by demons fervently begged to join him so he could be with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus wouldn’t allow this but replied, “Go to your family and friends; tell them everything the Ruler has done for you and how he had mercy on you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;So the man began spreading the news all around the ten towns in the region,&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit. the “region-of-ten-cities” that was located east of the Jordan River&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; explaining how Jesus had done so much for him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone was amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Two illustrations about touch…&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus returned to the other side in a boat,  a huge crowd joined him by the sea.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And a synagogue ruler named Jairus arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Jairus saw Jesus he fell at Jesus’s feet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…imploring Jesus to touch others so they may be healed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Over and over Jairus begged, “My little daughter is about to die!  Please come!  Please reach out and touch her with your hands so she can be wholly well, so she can live!”&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: so she can be wholly well and live&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus went with Jairus.  A very large crowd followed–pressing in on Jesus from every side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…having the persistence to touch Jesus ourselves&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A particular woman in the crowd had blood oozing from her body for twelve years.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Having suffered through many doctors’ attempts to heal her she had spent all her money and hadn’t gotten any better.  Instead her symptoms grew worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But she heard about Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And she worked her way through the crowd behind Jesus and touched his clothes.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;She had said, “If I just touch his clothes, I will be well again!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately her flow of blood dried up and she realized that she had been healed from her sickness!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And immediately Jesus knew that mighty power had gone out from him so he turned around in the jostling crowd and asked, “Who touched my clothes?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;His students asked, “You see this large crowd pressing against you? And you say, ‘Who touched me?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus looked around him, trying to see the woman who had done this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The woman, realizing what had happened to her, came to Jesus.  Afraid and shaking, she fell down in front of him and told him the whole truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “Daughter, your expectant trust&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; has made you well.  Go in peace, be wholly well; your sickness that has tortured your body and heart&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;More literally: scourge; e.g.: the whip used by Roman soldiers to punish, torture, and intimidate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…persisting with Jesus until people are “raised from the dead”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;While Jesus was still speaking, messengers from the synagogue ruler’s home arrived with news.  “Your daughter is dead. Why bother the Teacher any more?” they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus, when he heard the news, immediately assured the synagogue ruler, “Don’t be afraid, only believe!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And Jesus asked that only Peter, James, and John the brother of James join him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they arrived at the synagogue ruler’s house Jesus saw a chaotic scene: people weeping and sobbing loudly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus entered the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why are you making a chaotic scene and weeping–the child isn’t dead, but is asleep?” Jesus asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They mocked Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after Jesus put them out of the house, he invited the girl’s father, mother, and those who were with him to join him; together they entered the place the child was lying.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Taking the child by her hand Jesus said, “Talitha cumi!”  (This translates to, “Little girl, I tell you, get up!“)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately the girl got up and walked; she was twelve years old.  And those present were deeply astonished and amazed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus strictly ordered those present not to tell a single person what had happened and instructed them to give the girl something to eat.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 6]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><span class="theme">Jesus couldn’t do miracles when there wasn’t expectant trust in him</span>
<small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>Jesus continued from Jairus’s home and entered his hometown; his disciples went with him.</p>
<p><small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>On the…<label for="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sd-less-than-em-greater" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote"><em>struck with astonishment</em></span></p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-6</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Jesus couldn’t do miracles when there wasn’t expectant trust in him&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus continued from Jairus’s home and entered his hometown; his disciples went with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;On the Sabbath day, Jesus started teaching in the synagogue and many people who heard him were surprised and amazed.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;struck with astonishment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Where did this man get these ideas?  What is this wisdom that is being given to him so that these miracles are being done through his hands?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Isn’t this the carpenter, Mary’s son, the brother of James, Joses, Judah, and Simon?  Aren’t his sisters living here too?” they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So they were offended&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;or scandalized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; at him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “A prophet isn’t dishonored–except in his own country, in his hometown, and among his own relatives.”  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus wasn’t able to do miracles there, except to lay his hands on a few sick people and heal them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He was amazed because of their lack of expectant trust&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faithlessness; or traditionally: unbelief&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; so he traveled around the towns in the area and spent his time teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…but the twelve obeyed Jesus in expectant trust&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus called the twelve, and began sending them out two by two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave them authority over the demons.&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;unclean spirits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He told them not to take anything for their journey except for a walking stick.  He didn’t allow them to take food, a wallet, or money.  He allowed them to wear sandals but not to bring extra clothes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to them,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever someone from a city offers their home as a place to stay, stay there until you leave their city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Whenever a city’s people will not receive you into one of their homes or hear your message, leave!  And shake off the dust that is under your feet for a legal witness against what they did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I say with certainty: it will be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Gen.19.NLT&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gen 19&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; on the day everyone’s acts and motives are judged&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or: in the day of judgement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; than for that city!] &lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The earliest and best copies of Mark’s manuscript do not contain this sentence but it does appear in Matthew’s telling of this story.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;xrefs&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bible.com/bible/116/Mat.10.1-15&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mat 10:1-15&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…and many people received the message with expectant trust&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went out and warned people to turn away from making selfish pleasure their primary life’s goal.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They cast out many demons; they anointed many with oil who were sick and healed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Herod was blind about Jesus:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;King Herod&lt;label for=&quot;md-herod-was-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-herod-was-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Herod was the corrupt puppet king the Romans had placed over Israel.&lt;/span&gt; heard this, for his name had become known, and he said, “John the Baptist has risen from the dead, and therefore these powers are at work in him.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But others said, “He is Elijah.” Others said, “He is a prophet, or like one of the prophets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Herod, when he heard this, said, “This is John, whom I beheaded. He has risen from the dead.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…because his personal pleasure was supreme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For Herod himself had sent out and arrested John and bound him in prison for the sake of Herodias, his brother Philip’s wife, for he had married her.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For John had said to Herod, “It is against God’s law for you to have your brother’s wife.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Herodias set herself against him and desired to kill him, but she couldn’t,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;for Herod feared John, knowing that he was a righteous and holy man, and kept him safe. When he heard him, he did many things, and he heard him gladly. &lt;label for=&quot;md-herod-likes-to-hear&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-herod-likes-to-hear&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Herod likes to hear about God, but refuses the seed John offers.  It’s not enough to enjoy hearing about God; we need to apply and practice what we learn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…because he placed political power over expectant trust&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then a convenient day came when Herod on his birthday made a supper for his nobles, the high officers, and the chief men of Galilee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the daughter of Herodias (also named Herodias) came in and danced, she pleased Herod and those sitting with him. The king said to the young lady, “Ask me whatever you want, and I will give it to you.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He swore to her, “Whatever you ask of me, I will give you, up to half of my kingdom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;She went out and said to her mother, “What shall I ask?”  Her mother replied, “The head of John the Baptist.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately Herodius hurried to the king and requested, “I want you to give me right now the head of John the Baptist on a platter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The king was exceedingly sorry, but for the sake of his oaths and of his dinner guests, he didn’t want to refuse her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;…until he killed the messenger sent to help him see&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately the king sent a soldier from his bodyguard to the prison with the command to bring back John’s head.  The soldier went to the prison and beheaded John,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; brought his head on a platter, and gave it to the young lady; and the young lady gave it to her mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When John’s students heard the news they came, claimed his body, and buried it in a tomb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The illustration of plentiful provision from emptiness&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The twelve ambassadors&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Traditionally ‘apostles’ but the word has fallen out of everyday spoken English.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-this-is-the-only&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-this-is-the-only&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is the only place Mark uses “ambassador”/“delegate” instead of “student” to refer to the twelve.&lt;/span&gt; returned to Jesus and told him all that they had done and taught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said, “Come with me; let’s go to an empty wilderness and rest awhile.  (There were many people who were coming and going and there wasn’t even enough spare time to eat!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;So Jesus and his students left in the boat, heading to an empty wilderness by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But the crowd saw them getting farther and farther away!  And many people from all the towns (along the way) recognized Jesus, ran to the empty wilderness place on foot, and arrived first!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus landed, he saw a very large crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Jesus’s heart broke for them because they were like sheep who were wandering without a shepherd–in danger for their lives.  So Jesus began teaching them many things.&lt;label for=&quot;md-or-maybe-from-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-or-maybe-from-the&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Or maybe from the students’ perspective: ‘began a very very long sermon’.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the day was nearly over, Jesus’s students came to him and said, “This place is a wilderness and the day is fading!&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;more literally: “the day is spent”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Send these people away!  Then they can go into the surrounding country, into the tiny villages, and buy themselves bread because they have nothing to eat!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus answered his students, “You give them something to eat!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They asked Jesus, “Should we go into the tiny villages&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The place where the disciples would go, “into the tiny villages,” is added here from the context&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and buy two hundred denarii—two hundred days’ wages—worth of bread and give them something to eat?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “How many loaves do you have?  Go see.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they found out they said, “Five loaves, and two fish!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus told everyone to sit down in groups on the green grass &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and they sat down in groups of hundreds and fifties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;The Bread is broken first, then the Fish are broken too&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus took the five loaves&lt;label for=&quot;md-looking-forward&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-looking-forward&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Looking forward, Jesus broke bread during his last supper with his students.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-14#22&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 14:22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and the two fish.&lt;label for=&quot;md-looking-backward&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-looking-backward&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;🔑 Looking backward, Jesus promised to teach his students to “fish” for people when he invited them to join him.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-1#17&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 1:17&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;md-a-theme-mark-begins&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-a-theme-mark-begins&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;A theme Mark begins developing is, “What did it mean for Jesus to be broken?  For us to be broken too?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking up to heaven, he blessed and broke the loaves, which he gave to his disciples to set before them.  He also divided the two fish among them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Everyone ate until they were full; &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;afterward the students gathered twelve baskets full of bread and fish!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Approximately five thousand men were in the crowd (in addition to women and children)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;People persistently call to Jesus; he is willing and able to meet each at their point of need&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately Jesus made his disciples enter the boat and go ahead of him to the other side, to Bethsaida, while he personally sent the huge crowd away.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;46&quot;&gt;46 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And after he had dismissed everyone, he climbed up the mountain to pray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;47&quot;&gt;47 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When evening arrive, the boat was in the middle of the sea and Jesus was alone on the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;48&quot;&gt;48 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Seeing his students deeply frustrated because they were rowing against the wind, a little before dawn&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lit: ‘about the fourth watch of the night’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Jesus came to them–walking on the sea.  He would have passed by them,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;49&quot;&gt;49 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;but when they saw Jesus walking on the sea they thought he was a ghost and cried out!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;50&quot;&gt;50 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They all saw him; all of them were afraid!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Jesus immediately called out to them, “Cheer up! I’m here! Don’t be afraid.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;51&quot;&gt;51 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He got into the boat with them and the wind suddenly stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the students were very amazed and astonished &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;52&quot;&gt;52 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;because they hadn’t understood about the loaves; instead their hearts were hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;53&quot;&gt;53 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they had crossed over, they landed at Gennesaret&lt;label for=&quot;md-this-is-the-same&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle &quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;md-this-is-the-same&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is the same region where Jesus cast out the ‘Legion’ of demons earlier.&lt;/span&gt; and moored to the shore. &lt;label class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mark-5&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mrk 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;54&quot;&gt;54 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They exited the boat and immediately the people recognized him!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;55&quot;&gt;55 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They ran all over the region and began to bring those who were sick on their mats to the locations where they heard Jesus was present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;56&quot;&gt;56 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Wherever Jesus entered—into villages, into cities, or into the country—they laid the sick in the marketplaces and begged him to just let them touch the fringe of his garment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And everyone who touched Jesus was made well. ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 7]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>Then the Pharisees and some of the scribes gathered together to him, having come from Jerusalem.  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>Now when they saw some of his disciples eating bread with defiled…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-7</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then the Pharisees and some of the scribes gathered together to him, having come from Jerusalem.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now when they saw some of his disciples eating bread with defiled, that is unwashed, hands, they found fault.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;(For the Pharisees and all the Jews don’t eat unless they wash their hands and forearms, holding to the tradition of the elders.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They don’t eat when they come from the marketplace unless they bathe themselves, and there are many other things which they have received to hold to: washings of cups, pitchers, bronze vessels, and couches.)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The Pharisees and the scribes asked him, “Why don’t your disciples walk according to the tradition of the elders, but eat their bread with unwashed hands?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He answered them, “Well did Isaiah prophesy of you hypocrites, as it is written, ‘This people honors me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They worship me in vain, teaching the commandments of men as if they were God’s principles and instructions.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“For you set aside the commandment of God, and hold tightly to the tradition of men—the washing of pitchers and cups, and you do many other such things.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Full well do you reject the commandment of God, that you may keep your tradition.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For Moses said, ‘Honor your father and your mother;’ and, ‘He who speaks evil of father or mother, let him be put to death.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But you say, ‘If a man tells his father or his mother, “Whatever profit you might have received from me is Corban,”’” (that is, he vowed to “give to God” what he would have given to them),  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“then you no longer allow him to do anything for his father or his mother,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;making void the word of God by your tradition which you have handed down. You do many things like this.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He called all the great crowd to himself and said to them, “Hear me, all of you, and understand.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;There is nothing from outside of the man that going into him can defile him; but the things which proceed out of the man are those that defile the man.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If anyone has ears to hear, let him carefully take this to heart!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When he had entered into a house away from the great crowd, his disciples asked him about the object lesson.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Are you also without understanding? Don’t you perceive that whatever goes into the man from outside can’t defile him,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;because it doesn’t go into his heart, but into his stomach, then into the latrine, making all foods clean?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said, “what proceeds out of the man, that defiles the man.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For from within, out of the hearts of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, sexual sins, murders, thefts,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;greed, wickedness, deceit, lustful desires, an evil eye, defaming God, pride, and foolishness.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;All these evil things come from within and defile the man.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;From there he got up and went away into the borders of Tyre and Sidon. He entered into a house and didn’t want anyone to know it, but he couldn’t escape notice.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For a woman whose little daughter had an unclean spirit, having heard of him, came and fell down at his feet.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now the woman was a Greek gentile, a Syrian-Phoenician by race. She begged him that he would cast the demon out of her daughter.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus said to her, “Let the children be filled first, for it is not appropriate to take the children’s bread and throw it to the dogs.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But she answered him, “Yes, Lord. Yet even the dogs under the table eat the children’s crumbs.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to her, “Because of this answer, go your way. The demon has gone out of your daughter.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;She went away to her house, and found the child having been laid on the bed, with the demon gone out.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Again he left the borders of Tyre and Sidon, and came to the sea of Galilee through the middle of the region of Decapolis (that is, the ten-cities-east-of-Jordan).  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They brought to him one who was deaf and had an impediment in his speech. They begged him to lay his hand on him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took him aside from the great crowd privately and put his fingers into his ears; and he spat and touched his tongue.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Looking up to heaven, he sighed, and said to him, “Ephphatha!” that is, “Be opened!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately his ears were opened, and the impediment of his tongue was released, and he spoke clearly.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He commanded them that they should tell no one, but the more he commanded them, so much the more widely they proclaimed it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were beyond amazed, saying, “He has done all things well. He makes even the deaf hear and the mute speak!” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 8]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>In those days, when there was an even larger crowd—and they had nothing to eat. Jesus called his disciples to himself and said to them,  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>“I have compassion on this…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-8</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-8</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In those days, when there was an even larger crowd—and they had nothing to eat. Jesus called his disciples to himself and said to them,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“I have compassion on this great crowd, because they have stayed with me now three days and have nothing to eat.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If I send them to their home without eating they will faint on the way, for some of them have come a long way.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;His disciples answered him, “From where could one satisfy these people with bread here in a deserted place?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He asked them, “How many loaves do you have?” They said, “Seven.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He commanded the great crowd to sit down on the ground, and he took the seven loaves. Having given thanks, he broke them and gave them to his disciples to serve, and they served the crowd.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They also had a few small fish. Having blessed them, he said to serve these also.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Everyone ate until they were full and the disciples gathered seven baskets of broken pieces that were left over.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Those who had eaten were about four thousand. Then Jesus sent them away.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately he entered into the boat with his disciples and came into the region of Dalmanutha.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The Pharisees came out and began to question him, requesting from him a sign from heaven to test him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He sighed deeply in his spirit and said, “Why does this generation ask for a sign? With certainty I tell you, no sign will be given to this generation.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He left them, and again entering into the boat, left for the other side.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They forgot to take bread; and they didn’t have more than one loaf in the boat with them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He warned them, saying, “Pay careful attention: beware of the yeast of the Pharisees and the yeast of Herod.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They reasoned with one another, saying, “It’s because we have no bread.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus, perceiving it, said to them, “Why do you reason that it’s because you have no bread? Don’t you perceive yet or understand? Is your heart still hardened?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Having eyes, don’t you see? Having ears, don’t you hear?&lt;/em&gt; Don’t you remember?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When I broke the five loaves among the five thousand, how many baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?” They told him, “Twelve.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“When the seven loaves fed the four thousand, how many baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?” They told him, “Seven.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He asked them, “Don’t you understand yet?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He came to Bethsaida. They brought a blind man to him and begged him to touch him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took hold of the blind man by the hand, and brought him out of the village. When he had spat on his eyes, and laid his hands on him, he asked him if he saw anything.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He looked up, and said, “I see men, but I see them like walking trees.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then again he laid his hands on his eyes. He looked intently, and was restored, and saw everyone clearly.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He sent him away to his house, saying, “Don’t enter into the village, nor tell anyone in the village.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus went out, with his disciples, into the villages of Caesarea Philippi. On the way he asked his disciples, “Who do men say that I am?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They told him, “John the Baptist, and others say Elijah, but others, one of the prophets.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “But who do you say that I am?” Peter answered, “You are the Messiah.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He commanded them that they should tell no one about him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He began to teach them that the Son of Man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, the chief priests, and the scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He spoke to them openly. Peter took him and began to reprimand him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But he, turning around and seeing his disciples, reprimanded Peter, and said, “Get behind me, Satan! For you have in mind not the things of God, but the things of men.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He called the great crowd to himself with his disciples and said to them, “Whoever wants to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For whoever wants to save his life will lose it; and whoever will lose his life for my sake and the sake of the Good News will save it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his life?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For what will a man give in exchange for his life?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For whoever will be ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of Man also will be ashamed of him when he comes in his Father’s glory with the holy angels.” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 10]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>He got up from there and came into the borders of Judea and beyond the Jordan. Large crowds came together to him again. And again—as he usually did—he taught them.  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-10</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-10</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He got up from there and came into the borders of Judea and beyond the Jordan. Large crowds came together to him again. And again—as he usually did—he taught them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pharisees came to him testing him, and asked him, “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He answered, “What did Moses command you?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They said, “Moses allowed a certificate of divorce to be written, and to divorce her.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus said to them, “For your hardness of heart, he wrote you this commandment.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But from the beginning of the creation, God made them male and female.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For this cause a man will leave his father and mother, and will join to his wife,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and the two will become one flesh, so that they are no longer two, but one flesh.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;What therefore God has joined together, let no man separate.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In the house, his disciples asked him again about the same matter.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If a woman herself divorces her husband and marries another, she commits adultery.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were bringing to him little children, that he should touch them, but the disciples reprimanded those who were bringing them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But when Jesus saw it, indignation rose in his heart and he said to his disciples, “Allow the little children to come to me! Don’t forbid them, for God’s Kingdom belongs to such as these.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;I tell you with complete certainty, whoever will not receive God’s Kingdom like a little child, he will in no way enter into it.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took them in his arms and blessed them, laying his hands on them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As he was starting on the way to Jerusalem, a man ran to him, knelt before him, and asked him, “Good Teacher, what shall I do that I may inherit eternal life?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to him, “Why do you call me good? No one is good except one—God.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;You know the commandments: ‘Do not murder,’ ‘Do not commit adultery,’ ‘Do not steal,’ ‘Do not give false testimony,’ ‘Do not cheat anyone,’ ‘Honor your father and mother.’”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to him, “Teacher, I have observed all these things from my youth.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus looking at him loved him, and said to him, “One thing you lack. Go, sell whatever you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me, taking up the cross.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But his face fell at that saying, and he went away sorrowful, for he was one who had great possessions.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus looked around and said to his disciples, “How difficult it is for those who have riches to enter into God’s Kingdom!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The disciples were amazed at his words. But Jesus answered again, “Children, how hard it is for those who trust in riches to enter into God’s Kingdom!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;It is easier for a camel to go through a needle’s eye than for a rich man to enter into God’s Kingdom.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were exceedingly amazed, saying to him, “Then who can be saved?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus, looking at them, said, “With men it is impossible, but not with God, for all things are possible with God.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Peter began to tell him, “Look! we have left all and have followed you.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said, “With certainty I tell you, there is no one who has left house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or land, for my sake, and for the sake of the Good News,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;but he will receive one hundred times more now in this time: houses, brothers, sisters, mothers, children, and land, with persecutions; and in the age to come eternal life.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But many who are first will be last, and the last first.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were on the way, going up to Jerusalem; and Jesus was going in front of them, and the disciples were amazed; and those who followed were afraid. He again took the twelve aside and began to tell them the things that were going to happen to him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Look! we are going up to Jerusalem. The Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests and the scribes. They will condemn him to death, and will deliver him to the Gentiles.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They will mock him, spit on him, scourge him, and kill him. On the third day he will rise again.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;James and John, the sons of Zebedee, approached him, saying, “Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever we will ask.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “What do you want me to do for you?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They said to him, “Grant to us that we may sit, one at your right hand and one at your left hand, in your glory.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus said to them, “You don’t know what you are asking. Are you able to drink the cup that I drink, and to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They said to him, “We are able.” Jesus said to them, “You shall indeed drink the cup that I drink, and you shall be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;but to sit at my right hand and at my left hand is not mine to give, but for whom it has been prepared.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the ten heard it, they began to be indignant towards James and John.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus summoned them and said to them, “You know that they who are recognized as rulers over the nations lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority over them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But it shall not be so among you, but whoever wants to become great among you shall be your servant.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Whoever of you wants to become first among you shall offer himself as slave of all.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For the Son of Man also came not to be served but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;46&quot;&gt;46 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They came to Jericho. As he went out from Jericho with his disciples and a great great crowd, a blind beggar named Bartimaeus (son of Timaeus), was sitting by the road.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;47&quot;&gt;47 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When he heard that it was Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out and say, “Jesus, you son of David, have mercy on me!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;48&quot;&gt;48 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Many reprimanded him, that he should be quiet, but he cried out much more, “You son of David, have mercy on me!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;49&quot;&gt;49 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus stood still and said, “Call him.” They called the blind man, saying to him, “Cheer up! Get up. He is calling you!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;50&quot;&gt;50 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He, casting away his cloak, sprang up, and came to Jesus.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;51&quot;&gt;51 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus asked him, “What do you want me to do for you?” The blind man said to him, “Rabboni, that I may see again.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;52&quot;&gt;52 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to him, “Go your way. Your expectant trust&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; has made you well.” Immediately he received his sight and followed Jesus on the way. ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 9]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>He said to them, “With certainty I tell you, there are some standing here who will in no way taste death until they see God’s Kingdom come with power.”  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>After six…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-9</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-9</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “With certainty I tell you, there are some standing here who will in no way taste death until they see God’s Kingdom come with power.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;After six days Jesus took with him Peter, James, and John, and brought them up onto a high mountain privately by themselves, and he was changed into another form in front of them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;His clothing became glistening, amazingly pure white, like snow, such as no launderer on earth can whiten them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Elijah and Moses appeared to them, and they were talking with Jesus.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Peter answered Jesus, “Rabbi, it is good for us to be here. Let’s make three tents: one for you, one for Moses, and one for Elijah.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For he didn’t know what to say, for they were very afraid.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A cloud came, overshadowing them, and a voice came out of the cloud, “This is my beloved Son. Listen to him.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Suddenly looking around, they saw no one with them any more, except Jesus only.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As they were coming down from the mountain, he commanded them that they should tell no one the things they had seen, until after the Son of Man had risen from the dead.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They kept this saying to themselves, questioning what the “rising from the dead” meant.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They asked him, saying, “Why do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Yes! Elijah comes first, and restores all things. (Yet why do the scriptures say regarding the Son of Man, that he should suffer many things and be treated with utter contempt?)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But I tell you that Elijah has come, and they have also done to him whatever they wanted to, even as it is written about him.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Coming to the disciples, he saw a great great crowd around them, and scribes questioning them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately all the great crowd, when they saw him, were greatly amazed, and running to him, greeted him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He asked the scribes, “What are you asking them?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;One of the people answered, “Teacher, I brought my son, who has a mute spirit;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and wherever it seizes him, it throws him down; and he foams at the mouth, grinds his teeth, and becomes rigid. I asked your disciples to cast it out, and they weren’t able.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He answered him, “Unbelieving generation, how long shall I be with you? How long shall I bear with you? Bring him to me.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They brought him to him, and when he saw him, immediately the spirit convulsed him and he fell on the ground, writhing and foaming at the mouth.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He asked his father, “How long has it been since this has been happening to him?” He said, “From childhood.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Often it has cast him both into the fire and into the water to destroy him. But if you can do anything, have compassion on us and help us.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to him, “If you can believe, all things are possible to him who believes.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately the father of the child cried out with tears, “I believe. Help my unbelief!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus saw that people were running to join the crowd, he reprimanded the unclean spirit, saying to him, “You mute and deaf spirit, I command you, come out of him, and never enter him again!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;After crying out and convulsing him greatly, it came out of him. The boy became like one dead, so much that most of them said, “He is dead.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus took him by the hand and raised him up; and he got up.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When he had come into the house, his disciples asked him privately, “Why couldn’t we cast it out?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “This kind cannot come out but by prayer and fasting.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went out from there and passed through Galilee. He didn’t want anyone to know it,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;for he was teaching his disciples, and said to them, “The Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of his enemies, and they will kill him; and when he is killed, on the third day he will rise again.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But they didn’t understand the saying, and were afraid to ask him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He came to Capernaum, and when he was in the house he asked them, “What were you arguing among yourselves on the way?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But they were silent, for they had disputed with one another on the way about who was the greatest.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He sat down and called the twelve; and he said to them, “If any man wants to be first, he shall be last of all, and servant of all.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took a little child and set him in the middle of them. Taking him in his arms, he said to them,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Whoever receives one such little child in my name receives me; and whoever receives me, doesn’t receive me, but him who sent me.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;John said to him, “Teacher, we saw someone who doesn’t follow us casting out demons in your name; and we forbade him, because he doesn’t follow us.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus said, “Don’t forbid him, for there is no one who will do a mighty work in my name and be able to speak evil of me soon afterward.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For whoever is not against us is on our side.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For whoever will give you a cup of water to drink in my name because you belong to the Messiah, most certainly I tell you, he will in no way lose his reward.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Whoever will cause one of these little ones who believe in me to stumble, it would be better for him if he were thrown into the sea with a millstone hung around his neck.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If your hand causes you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life maimed, rather than having your two hands to go into Gehenna, into the unquenchable fire,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;‘where their worm doesn’t die, and the fire is not quenched.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life lame, rather than having your two feet to be cast into Gehenna, into the fire that will never be quenched—  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;46&quot;&gt;46 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;‘where their worm doesn’t die, and the fire is not quenched.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;47&quot;&gt;47 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If your eye causes you to stumble, throw it out. It is better for you to enter into God’s Kingdom with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the Gehenna of fire,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;48&quot;&gt;48 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;‘where their worm doesn’t die, and the fire is not quenched.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;49&quot;&gt;49 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For everyone will be salted with fire, and every sacrifice will be seasoned with salt.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;50&quot;&gt;50 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Salt is good, but if the salt has lost its flavor, how can a person add its character back? Have salt’s qualities in yourselves, and be at peace with one another.” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 11]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>When they approached Jerusalem, they came to Bethsphage and Bethany at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>and said to them, “Go your way into the…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-11</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-11</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they approached Jerusalem, they came to Bethsphage and Bethany at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and said to them, “Go your way into the village that is opposite you. Immediately as you enter into it, you will find a young donkey tied, on which no one has sat. Untie him and bring him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If anyone asks you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ say, ‘The Lord needs him;’ and immediately he will send him back here.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went away, and found a young donkey tied at the door outside in the open street, and they untied him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Some of those who stood there asked them, “What are you doing, untying the young donkey?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They said to them just as Jesus had said, and they let them go.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They brought the young donkey to Jesus and threw their garments on it, and Jesus sat on it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Many spread their garments on the way, and others were cutting down branches from the trees and spreading them on the road.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Those who went in front and those who followed cried out, “Hosanna! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Blessed is the kingdom of our father David that is coming in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus entered into the temple in Jerusalem. When he had looked around at everything, because it was evening he left Jerusalem and returned to Bethany with the twelve.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The next day, when they had left Bethany’s town boundaries he was hungry.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Seeing a fig tree far away off having leaves, he came to see if perhaps he might find anything on it. When he came to it, he found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season for figs.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus told it, “May no one ever eat fruit from you again!” and his disciples heard it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They came to Jerusalem, and Jesus entered into the temple and began to throw out those who sold and those who bought in the temple, and overthrew the money changers’ tables and the seats of those who sold the doves.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He would not allow anyone to carry merchandise through the temple.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He taught, saying to them, “Isn’t it written, &lt;em&gt;‘My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations?’&lt;/em&gt; But you have made it a den of robbers!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The chief priests and the scribes heard it, and searched for how they could destroy him. For they feared him because all the great crowd was amazed at his teaching.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When evening came, he went out of the city.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As they passed by in the morning, they saw the fig tree withered away from the roots.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Peter, remembering, said to him, “Rabbi, look! The fig tree which you cursed has withered away.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered them, “Have expectant trust&lt;label for=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sd-less-than-em-greater&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in God.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For most certainly I tell you, whoever may tell this mountain, ‘Be taken up and cast into the sea,’ and doesn’t doubt in his heart, but believes that what he says is happening, he shall have whatever he says.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Therefore I tell you, all things whatever you pray and ask for, believe that you have received them, and you shall have them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Whenever you stand praying, forgive, if you have anything against anyone; so that your Father, who is in heaven, may also forgive you your wrongdoings.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in heaven forgive your wrongdoings.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They came again to Jerusalem, and as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders came to him,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and they began saying to him, “By what authority do you do these things? Or who gave you this authority to do these things?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to them, “I will ask you one question. Answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The baptism of John—was it from heaven, or from men? Answer me.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They reasoned with themselves, saying, “If we should say, ‘From heaven;’ he will say, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;If we should say, ‘From men’“—they feared the people, for all held John to really be a prophet.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They answered Jesus, “We don’t know.” Jesus said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things.” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 12]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>He began to speak to them in object lessons. “A man planted a vineyard, put a hedge around it, dug a pit for the wine press, built a tower, rented it out to a farmer…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-12</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-12</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He began to speak to them in object lessons. “A man planted a vineyard, put a hedge around it, dug a pit for the wine press, built a tower, rented it out to a farmer, and went into another country.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When it was time, he sent a servant to the farmer to get from the farmer his share of the fruit of the vineyard.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They took him, beat him, and sent him away empty.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Again, he sent another servant to them; and they threw stones at him, wounded him in the head, and sent him away shamefully treated.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Again he sent another, and they killed him, and many others, beating some, and killing some.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Therefore still having one, his beloved son, he sent him last to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But those farmers said among themselves, ‘This is the heir. Come, let’s kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They took him, killed him, and cast him out of the vineyard.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the farmers, and will give the vineyard to others.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Haven’t you even read this Scripture: &lt;em&gt;‘The stone which the builders rejected was made the head of the corner. *  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;This was from the Lord. It is marvelous in our eyes’?“*  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They tried to seize him, but they feared the great crowd; for they perceived that he spoke the object lesson against them. They left him and went away.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They sent some of the Pharisees and the Herodians to him, that they might trap him with words.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they had come, they asked him, “Teacher, we know that you are honest, and don’t defer to anyone; for you aren’t partial to anyone, but truly teach the way of God. Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar, or not?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Shall we give, or shall we not give?” But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, “Why do you test me? Bring me Roman coin (a denarius), that I may see it.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They brought it. He said to them, “Whose is this image and inscription?” They said to him, “Caesar’s.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered them, “Give Caesar the things that are Caesar’s, and to God the things that are God’s.” They were greatly amazed at him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Some Sadducees, who say that there is no resurrection, came to him. They asked him, saying,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Teacher, Moses wrote to us, ‘If a man’s brother dies and leaves a wife behind him, and leaves no children, that his brother should take his wife and raise up offspring for his brother.’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;There were seven brothers. The first took a wife, and dying left no offspring.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The second took her, and died, leaving no children behind him. The third likewise;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and the seven took her and left no children. Last of all the woman also died.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In the resurrection, when they rise, whose wife will she be of them? For the seven had her as a wife.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered them, “Isn’t this because you are mistaken, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For when they will rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels in heaven.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But about the dead, that they are raised: haven’t you read in the book of Moses in the story about the burning bush, how God spoke to him, saying, ‘I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob’?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. You are badly mistaken!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;One of the scribes came and heard them questioning together, and knowing that he had answered them well, asked him, “Which commandment is the greatest of all?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered, “The greatest is: &lt;em&gt;‘Hear, Israel, the Lord our God, the Lord is one. *  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, with all your mind, and with all your strength.’* This is the first commandment.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The second is like this: &lt;em&gt;‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’&lt;/em&gt; There is no other commandment greater than these.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The scribe said to him, “Truly, teacher, you have said well that he is one, and there is none other but he;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and to love him with all the heart, with all the understanding, all the soul, and with all the strength, and to love his neighbor as himself, is more important than all whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus saw that he answered wisely, he said to him, “You are not far from God’s Kingdom.” No one dared ask him any question after that.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus responded as he taught in the temple, “How is it that the scribes say that the Messiah is the son of David?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For David himself said in the Holy Spirit, &lt;em&gt;‘The Lord said to my Lord, “Sit at my right hand, until I make your enemies the footstool of your feet.“’&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Therefore David himself calls him Lord, so how can he be his son?” The common people heard him gladly.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;In his teaching he said to them, “Beware of the scribes, who like to walk in long robes, and to be greeted in the marketplaces,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and to have the best seats in the synagogues and the best places at feasts,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;those who devour widows’ houses, and for a pretense make long prayers. These will receive greater condemnation.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus sat down opposite the treasury and saw how the great crowd cast money into the treasury. Many who were rich cast in much.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A poor widow came and she cast in two small brass coins (which equal a quadrans coin).  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus called his disciples close and said to them, “With certainty I tell you, this poor widow gave more than all those who are giving into the treasury,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;for they all gave out of their abundance, but she, out of her poverty, gave all that she had to live on.” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 13]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>As he went out of the temple, one of his disciples said to him, “Teacher, see what kind of stones and what kind of buildings!”  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>Jesus said to him, “Do you see these…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-13</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-13</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As he went out of the temple, one of his disciples said to him, “Teacher, see what kind of stones and what kind of buildings!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to him, “Do you see these great buildings? There will not be left here one stone on another, which will not be thrown down.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As he sat on the Mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter, James, John, and Andrew asked him privately,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Tell us, when will these things happen? What is the sign that these things are all about to be fulfilled?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus replied, “Be careful that no one misleads you.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am he!’ and will mislead many.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“When you hear of wars and rumors of wars, don’t be troubled. For those must happen, but the end is not yet.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be earthquakes in various places. There will be famines and troubles. These things are the beginning of birth pains.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“But watch yourselves, for they will deliver you up to councils. You will be beaten in synagogues. You will stand before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The Good News must first be declared to all the nations.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they lead you away and deliver you up, don’t be anxious beforehand or premeditate what you will say, but say whatever will be given you in that hour. For it is not you who speak, but the Holy Spirit.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Brother will deliver up brother to death, and the father his child. Children will rise up against parents and cause them to be put to death.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;You will be hated by all men for my name’s sake, but he who endures to the end will be saved.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“But when you see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing where it ought not” (let the reader understand), “then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and let the person on the housetop not go down, enter, or take anything out of his house.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The person out in the field must not return even to get his coat.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;How terrible it will be for women who are pregnant or who nurse babies in those days!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pray that your escape won’t be in the winter.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For in those days there will be oppression unlike anyone has known from the earliest beginning of God’s creation until now. And it will never will be that great again.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Unless the Lord had shortened the days, nobody would have been saved. But for the sake of the chosen ones—whom the Lord himself picked out—he shortened the days.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then if anyone tells you, ‘Look, here is the Messiah!’ or, ‘Look, there!’ don’t believe it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For false “messiahs” and false “prophets” will arise, will show signs and wonders, and will try to lead—if possible—even the chosen ones down their false and corrupt path.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But you watch. “Look! I have told you about all these things beforehand.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But in those days, after that oppression, *the sun will be darkened, the moon will not give its light, *  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;the stars will be falling from the sky, and the powers that are in the heavens will be shaken.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then they will see the Son of Man coming in clouds with great power and glory.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then he will send out his angels, and will gather together his chosen ones from the four winds, from the ends of the earth to the ends of the sky.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“Now learn this object lesson from the fig tree: When its branch becomes tender and produces its leaves, you know that its summer is near;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;even so you also, when you see these things happening, know that your summer is near, at the doors.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Most certainly I say to you, this generation will not pass away until all these things happen.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will not pass away.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“But of that day or that hour no one knows—not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Watch, keep alert, and pray; for you don’t know when the time is.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“It is like a man traveling to another country, having left his house and given authority to each of his servants to do his work, and having also commanded the doorkeeper to keep watch.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Therefore watch, for you don’t know when the lord of the house is coming—whether at evening, at midnight, when the rooster crows, or in the morning;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Otherwise when he comes suddenly he might find you sleeping.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;What I tell you, I tell all: Watch!” ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 14]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>It was now two days before the Passover and the Feast of Unleavened Bread, and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might seize him by deception and kill…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-14</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-14</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;It was now two days before the Passover and the Feast of Unleavened Bread, and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might seize him by deception and kill him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For they said, “Not during the feast, because there might be a riot among the people.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Meanwhile Jesus was in Bethany in the house of Simon (a man who previously had been a leper). As Jesus sat, eating at the table, a woman came having a beautiful alabaster jar of expensive aromatic oil made using pure nard. She broke the jar and poured it over his head.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But there were some who were indignant among themselves, saying, “Why has this expensive perfumed oil been wasted?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For this might have been sold for more than three hundred denarii (an entire year’s wages) and given to the poor!” So they criticized her.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Jesus said, “Leave her alone. Why do you trouble her? She has done a good work for me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For you always have the poor with you, and whenever you want to, you can do them good; but you will not always have me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;She has done what she could and has anointed my body for burial ahead of time.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;With certainty I tell you, wherever this Good News is declared throughout the whole world, what this woman has done will be remembered and retold in memory of her.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then Judas Iscariot, who was one of the twelve, found to the chief priests in order to discuss how he could betray Jesus to them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For their part, when they heard this, they were glad and promised to give him money. And Judas began searching for an opportune moment to betray Jesus.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;On the first day of unleavened bread, when they sacrificed the Passover, his disciples asked him, “Where do you want us to go and prepare that you may eat the Passover?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He sent two of his disciples and said to them, “Enter the city, and a man carrying a pitcher of water will meet you. Follow him,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;and wherever he enters, tell the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says, “Where is the guest room, where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?“’  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He will himself show you a large upper room furnished and ready. Make preparations there.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus’s disciples entered the city and found things exactly the way Jesus had told them, and they prepared the Passover.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When it was evening he arrived with the twelve.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As they at the table eating, Jesus said, “With certainty I tell you, one of you will betray me—even one who eats with me here.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They became full of grief, and began to ask him one by one, “Surely not I?” And another said, “Surely not I?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered, “It is one of you twelve who eats from this dish along with me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;For the Son of Man must die in the same way as it was written in the Scriptures. But intense grieving misery will come to that man who betrays the Son of Man! It would be better for that man if he had not been born.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As they were eating, Jesus took bread, and when he had blessed it, he broke it and gave to them, and said, “Take, eat. This is my body.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took the cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave to them. They all drank of it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “This is my blood of the new covenant, which is poured out for many.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;With certainty I tell you, I will never drink of the fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it again in God’s Kingdom.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to them, “All of you will be made to stumble because of me tonight, for it is written, &lt;em&gt;‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered.’&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;However, after I am raised up, I will go before you into Galilee.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Peter said to him, “Even if all other people desert you, I will not.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said to him, “With certainty I tell you that you today that even this night—before the rooster crows twice—you will deny me three times.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Peter protested all the more, “If I must die with you, I will not deny you!” They all vowed the same thing.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They came to a place which was named Gethsemane. He said to his disciples, “Sit here while I pray.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He took with him Peter, James, and John, and became greatly troubled and distressed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “My heart grieves so deeply—even to the point of death! Stay here with me and watch.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He went forward a little, and fell to the ground, and prayed that if it were possible, the terrible hour prepared for him might pass him by.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He prayed, “Daddy! Father! All things are possible to you. Please remove this cup from me. However, not what I desire, but what you desire.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He came back and finding them sleeping said to Peter, “Simon, are you sleeping? Couldn’t you watch one hour?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Watch and pray, that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit is very willing, but ‘human strength’ is weak.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Again he went away and prayed, saying the same words.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Again he returned and found them sleeping, for their eyes were very heavy; and they didn’t know how to reply to him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He came the third time and said to them, “Sleep on now, and take your rest. It is enough. The time has come. Look! the Son of Man is being betrayed into the power of evil people.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Get up! Let’s get going. Look! The one who is betraying me has arrived.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately, while he was still speaking, Judas, one of the twelve, came—and with him a great crowd with swords and clubs, from the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now the one who betrayed Jesus had told them to watch for this signal: He said, “Whoever I kiss, he is the one. Arrest him and lead him away safely.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Judas arrived, immediately he came up to Jesus and said, “Rabbi! Rabbi!” and kissed him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;46&quot;&gt;46 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They grabbed him and seized him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;47&quot;&gt;47 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But a person who stood by drew his sword, struck the servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;48&quot;&gt;48 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus answered them, “Have you come as if you were chasing a robber and needed swords and clubs to seize me?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;49&quot;&gt;49 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;I was with you in the temple every day teaching, and you didn’t arrest me. But this has happened so that the Scriptures could be fulfilled.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;50&quot;&gt;50 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They all his disciples abandoned him and fled.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;51&quot;&gt;51 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A certain young man followed him and all he was weaaring was a linen cloth thrown around his naked body. The mob grabbed him!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;52&quot;&gt;52 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But he left the linen cloth and fled from them naked.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;53&quot;&gt;53 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They led Jesus away to the high priest’s house where all the chief priests, elders, and scribes were joining them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;54&quot;&gt;54 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Peter had followed Jesus from a distance, until he came into the courtyard of the high priest’s home. He sat along with the officers, warming himself in the light of the fire.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;55&quot;&gt;55 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now the chief priests and the whole council searched for witnesses who could testify against Jesus so they could put him to death. But they couldn’t find any  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;56&quot;&gt;56 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;because although many people gave false testimony against him, their stories didn’t agree with each other!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;57&quot;&gt;57 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Some stood before those assembled and offered this false testimony against Jesus:  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;58&quot;&gt;58 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;“We heard him say, ‘I will destroy this temple that is made with hands, and in three days I will build another made without hands.’”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;59&quot;&gt;59 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But they even disagreed in their testimony about this!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;60&quot;&gt;60 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Finally the high priest stood up in the middle of the assembly and asked Jesus, “Don’t you have anything to say? How will you respond to these accusations against you?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;61&quot;&gt;61 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But he stayed quiet, and didn’t answer. Again the high priest asked Jesus, “Are you the Messiah, the Son of the Blessed One?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;62&quot;&gt;62 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus said, &lt;em&gt;“I Am.&lt;/em&gt; And you will see the Son of Man sitting in the seat of highest power and authority and coming with the clouds of the sky.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;63&quot;&gt;63 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The high priest tore his clothes and said, “Do we need witnesses any longer?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;64&quot;&gt;64 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;You have heard him defaming God by claiming to be God himself! What do you think?” They unanimously declared Jesus guilty, fully deserving death.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;65&quot;&gt;65 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Some began to spit on him, to cover his face, to beat him with fists, and to order him, “Prophesy!” Then the officers struck him with the palms of their hands.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;66&quot;&gt;66 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;As Peter was in the courtyard below, one of the maids of the high priest came.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;67&quot;&gt;67 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When she noticed Peter warming himself, she looked intently at him and said, “You were also with the Nazarene, Jesus!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;68&quot;&gt;68 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But he denied it! “I don’t know or understand what you are saying”, Peter answered. He went out on the porch, and the rooster crowed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;69&quot;&gt;69 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The maid saw him on the porch and insisted again to the other onlookers, “This man is one of them!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;70&quot;&gt;70 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Peter again denied it! And just a little bit later those who were milling around said to Peter, “You must be one of them because you are from Galilee! Your accent gives you away!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;71&quot;&gt;71 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But Peter began to curse and to swear, “I don’t know this man you’re talking about!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;72&quot;&gt;72 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Then the rooster crowed the second time. Peter remembered that Jesus had told him, “Before the rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times.” And Peter broke down weeping. ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 16]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>When the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James, and Salome bought spices, that they might come and anoint him.  <small><sup class="verse" id="2">2 </sup></small>Very early on the first day…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-16</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-16</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James, and Salome bought spices, that they might come and anoint him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Very early on the first day of the week, they came to the tomb when the sun had risen.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They were saying among themselves, “Who will roll away the stone from the door of the tomb for us?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;for it was very big. Looking up, they saw that the stone was rolled back.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Entering into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, dressed in a white robe; and they were amazed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Don’t be amazed. You seek Jesus, the Nazarene, who has been crucified. He has risen! He is not here. See the place where they laid him!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But go, tell his disciples and Peter, ‘He goes before you into Galilee. There you will see him, as he said to you.’”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went out, and fled from the tomb, for trembling and astonishment had come on them. They said nothing to anyone; for they were afraid.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now when he had risen early on the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had cast out seven demons.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;She went and told those who had been with him, as they mourned and wept.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they heard that he was alive and had been seen by her, they disbelieved.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;After these things he was revealed in another form to two of them as they walked, on their way into the country.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went away and told it to the rest. They didn’t believe them, either.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Afterward he was revealed to the eleven themselves as they sat at the table; and he reprimanded them for their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they didn’t believe those who had seen him after he had risen.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He said to them, “Go into all the world and declare the Good News to the whole creation.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;He who believes and is baptized will be saved; but he who disbelieves will be condemned.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;These signs will accompany those who believe: in my name they will cast out demons; they will speak with new languages;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;they will take up serpents; and if they drink any deadly thing, it will in no way hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick, and they will recover.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;So then the Lord, after he had spoken to them, was received up into heaven and sat down at the right hand of God.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They went out and spoke God’s word everywhere, the Lord working with them and confirming the word by the signs that followed. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mark 15]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><small><sup class="verse" id="1">1 </sup></small>Immediately in the morning the chief priests with the elders, scribes, and the whole council consulted together, bound Jesus, carried him away, and transferred him as a…</p>]]></description><link>https://thebeginning.life//mark-15</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebeginning.life//mark-15</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Immediately in the morning the chief priests with the elders, scribes, and the whole council consulted together, bound Jesus, carried him away, and transferred him as a prisoner to Pilate. Pilate was the region’s Roman governor.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate asked Jesus, “Are you the King of the Jews?” He answered, “So you say.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The chief priests accused him of many crimes.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate asked him again, “Don’t you have any answers for them? They are accusing you of many crimes!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus didn’t answer. And Pilate was amazed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Now at the feast Pilate customarily pardoned and released one prisoner—one who they requested by name.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;And Pilate was holding an insurgent named Barabbas (his name means “Son of the Father”) along with others who rebelled along with him. They were all murderers.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The great crowd roared loudly for Pilate to release a prisoner as he customarily did during the feast.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate answered, “Do you want me to release to you the King of the Jews?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;(because Pilate sensed that the chief priests had really arrested Jesus because they were jealous of him).  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;11 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;But the chief priests riled up the mob so that they all demanded that Pilate release Barabbas to them instead.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;12 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate responded, “Then what should I do to the man you call the King of the Jews?”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;13 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They roared back, “Crucify him!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;14 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate said to them, “Why? What crime did he commit?” But they roared back even louder, “Crucify him!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;15&quot;&gt;15 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate wanted to appease the mob, so he released Barabbas to them. And after he flogged Jesus with a lead-tipped whip, Pilate released him to Roman soldiers to be crucified.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;16&quot;&gt;16 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The soldiers led Jesus away to the great courtyard (named the Praetorium), then called for the entire regiment.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;17&quot;&gt;17 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The regiment clothed Jesus in royal purple, weaved a crown made of thorns, and pressed it on his head.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;18&quot;&gt;18 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They saluteed and taunted him, saying “Hail, King of the Jews!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;19&quot;&gt;19 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They struck his head with a stick that came from a reed. They spat on him. And bowing their knees, they “paid homage” to him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;20&quot;&gt;20 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When they had mocked him in these ways, they took the purple robe off him and dressed him in his own clothes. And the soldiers led Jesus out to crucify him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;21&quot;&gt;21 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;On the way, the soldiers chose a man who happened to be passing by on his way from the country (Simon of Cyrene, the father of Alexander and Rufus). They forced him to join them and carry Jesus’s cross.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;22&quot;&gt;22 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They brought Jesus to the place called Golgotha. This name means, “Place of the skull.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;23&quot;&gt;23 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The soldiers offered him wine drugged with myrrh, but Jesus wouldn’t drink it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;24&quot;&gt;24 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;They crucified Jesus—they nailed him to a cross. And they gambled together to decide who would get each piece of his clothes.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;25&quot;&gt;25 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;It was the third hour—about 9 o’clock—when they crucified Jesus.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;26&quot;&gt;26 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;A sign with his crime was fastened above him. It read, “THE KING OF THE JEWS.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;27&quot;&gt;27 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Along with Jesus, the soldiers crucified two robbers—one on his right hand, and one to his left.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;28&quot;&gt;28 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;[This fulfilled the Scripture that says, &lt;em&gt;“He was counted alongside those who live lawlessly.”]&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;29&quot;&gt;29 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Those who passed by defamed him, shook their heads and hurled insults, “Ha! You who destroy the temple and build it in three days,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;30&quot;&gt;30 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;save yourself! Come down from the cross!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;31&quot;&gt;31 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Similarly, the chief priests mocked him among themselves and with the scribes. They said, “He saved others. He can’t save himself!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;32&quot;&gt;32 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Let the Messiah, the King of Israel, now come down from the cross, that we may see and believe him.” Those who were crucified with him also insulted him.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;33&quot;&gt;33 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the sixth hour had come (about noon), there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour, or approximately 3 P.M.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;34&quot;&gt;34 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;At the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, &lt;em&gt;“Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani?”&lt;/em&gt; which means, *“My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?” *  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;35&quot;&gt;35 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Some stood by heard this and said, “Look! he is calling Elijah.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;36&quot;&gt;36 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;One ran and filled a sponge full of vinegar. He put it on the end of a stick and offered it to Jesus to drink, saying, “Leave him alone. Let’s see whether Elijah comes to take him down!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;37&quot;&gt;37 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Jesus cried out with a loud voice, and breathed his last breath.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;38&quot;&gt;38 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;The temple curtain (that separated the Most Holy Place from the rest) was torn in two from the top to the bottom.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;39&quot;&gt;39 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When the Roman centurion standing guard saw that Jesus cried out like this and then breathed his last breath, he said, “This man really was God’s Son!”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;40&quot;&gt;40 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;There were women watching from far away including Mary Magdalene, Mary (the mother of James the Younger and of Joseph), and Salome.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;41&quot;&gt;41 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When Jesus was in Galilee, these women travelled with him and supported him. Also, many other women who came to Jerusalem with Jesus were there.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;42&quot;&gt;42 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;When evening arrived, because it was the Preparation Day—that is, the day before the Sabbath—  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;43&quot;&gt;43 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Joseph of Arimathaea boldly went to Pilate, and asked for Jesus’ body. (Joseph was a prominent council member who was also looking for God’s Kingdom.)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;44&quot;&gt;44 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Pilate was surprised to hear that Jesus was already dead; and summoning the centurion, he asked him whether Jesus had been dead long.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;45&quot;&gt;45 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;After discussing this with the centurion, he granted Jesus’s body to Joseph.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;46&quot;&gt;46 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Joseph bought a linen cloth, and taking him down, wound him in the linen cloth and laid him in a tomb which had been cut out of a rock. He rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;verse&quot; id=&quot;47&quot;&gt;47 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses, saw where he was laid. ﻿&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><author>dvorme@gmail.com</author></item></channel></rss>